Well, welcome back to Jupyter Lab for what will be an epic finale to our time in this platform.
さて､ Jupyter Labにようこそ！このプラットフォームでの時間の壮大なフィナーレを飾ることになるだろう｡
And it's going to be such a great conclusion to the last seven weeks.
そして､ この7週間を締めくくる素晴らしいものになるだろう｡
The first thing you'll notice is that there is quite a lot going on in the week eight folder.
まず気づくのは､ 8週目のフォルダーにはかなり多くのことが起こっているということだ｡
There are a lot of files here, which reflects the fact that we've got a lot to get through, a lot
これは､ この大きな問題を解決するために､ 私たちが多くの仕事をこなさなければならないという事実を反映している｡
It means I'm going to be moving at a faster pace than usual as we go through this code.
つまり､ このコードを読み進めるにあたって､ いつもより速いペースで進むということだ｡
But that's okay, because at this point you are proficient, you're well on your way to mastering LLM
でも大丈夫､ この時点であなたはLLMエンジニアリングをマスターしているのだから｡
engineering, and you no longer need me to belabor the point about lists of dicts of assistants and
アシスタントのディクテットやユーザーのリストなど､ もはや私が長々と説明する必要はない｡
It's it's now something that is very much old news.
それはもう､ 非常に古いニュースだ｡
And yeah, it's amazing to think I was explaining what tokens were only, only a matter of weeks ago.
ほんの数週間前まで､ トークンが何なのかを説明していたなんて｡
And and now that you're ready for a big, full on agentic AI I.
そして今､ あなたは大規模な､ 完全なエージェントAI Iの準備ができている｡
Solution a quick admin point before we get started.
始める前に､ 簡単な管理上の注意点を説明しよう｡
Uh, the I've made some changes to the packages.
パッケージを少し変更したんだ｡
I've added some more packages that are dependencies on this environment in order to, to really make
この環境に依存するパッケージをいくつか追加した｡
And that just means you might need if you've if you pulled the code sometime before like late September,
つまり､ 9月下旬以前にコードを取得した場合は､ 私が追加した新機能を追加するために､ 再度コードを取得し､
you might need to pull the code again and update your packages to have anything new that I've added.
パッケージを更新する必要があるかもしれないということだ｡
And that's very easy to do.
それはとても簡単なことだ｡
Um, all you have to do, of course, is go to the project home directory.
もちろん､ プロジェクトのホーム・ディレクトリに行けばいいだけだ｡
So LM engineering.
だからLMエンジニアリングだ｡
Um, and if you're on a PC, then you need to be in an Anaconda prompt.
PCを使っているなら､ Anacondaプロンプトに入る必要があります｡
Uh, and then you do a git pull to get the latest code, and then you run conda env update.
それからgit pullして最新のコードを取得し､ conda env updateを実行する｡
Um, you specify the file as environment.yml and the dash dash prune tells it to remove any packages
ええと､ ファイルをenvironmentとして指定します｡  ymlとdash dash pruneは､ リストにもうないパッケージを削除するように指示する｡
I don't think I have removed anything, but anyways, I think this is always a sensible uh, one liner.
私は何も削除していないと思うが､ とにかく､ これは常に賢明なあー､ ワンライナーだと思う｡
Good to have that to hand to update your environment with a new environment.yml file.
新しい環境にアップデートするために､ それを手元に置いておくのは良いことだ｡  ymlファイル｡
Okay, so here we go.
さて､ それでは始めよう｡
Let's talk about modal.
モーダルについて話そう｡
So as we get into today's class there only is one import to begin with.
だから今日の授業では､ まず輸入品は1つしかない｡
And it is to import modal.
そして､ モーダルをインポートすることである｡
There we go.
これでよし｡
Now if you have not set up your tokens which you will not have done, then you need to run a command
トークンをセットアップしていない場合は､ モーダルセットアップと呼ばれるコマンドラインを実行する必要があります｡
And the way you can run that is you just uncomment this line and you run that statement right there.
その実行方法は､ この行のコメントを解除して､ そのステートメントを実行するだけだ｡
Now I'm not going to do it because I've already done it and my environment set up.
今､ 私はそれをするつもりはない｡ なぜなら､ 私の環境はすでにセットアップされているからだ｡
But when you do, it's going to pop up with a browser window and have you authorize modal.
しかし､ そうすると､ ブラウザ・ウィンドウがポップアップし､ モーダルを承認しなければならなくなる｡
And then modal will set your environment variables for you.
そして､ モーダルがあなたの代わりに環境変数を設定する｡
And I think that's really great.
それは本当に素晴らしいことだと思う｡
All of the challenges that people have had with tokens, particularly with OpenAI, this is a very different
トークン､ 特にOpenAIで人々が抱えていた課題はすべて､ これはまったく異なる経験だ｡
It's really streamlined.
実に合理的だ｡
So good for modal.
モーダルにはとてもいい｡
They seem to have really figured out the the way to set tokens.
彼らはトークンをセットする方法を本当に理解しているようだ｡
If for any reason that doesn't work for you, then if you go into the modal platform, you can actually
何らかの理由でそれがうまくいかない場合は､ モーダルプラットフォームに行けば､ OpenAIのようなものと同じように､
find your tokens in there in much the same way as you can for for things like OpenAI.
トークンを見つけることができます｡
And then you can manually set it.
そして､ 手動で設定することができる｡
Um, but hopefully this will just work.
うーん､ でもうまくいけばいいんだけど
It certainly did for me.
確かに私にはそうだった｡
And by all accounts, that's that's how it works for for people generally.
誰の目から見ても､ それが一般的な人々のための方法だ｡
All right.
分かった｡
So now, uh, in the next line, I'm going to import some things from a package called hello, which
次の行では､ helloというパッケージからいくつかのものをインポートします｡
And I'm going to take you over to that right now to show you what it looks like.
これから､ その様子をお見せしましょう｡
So this is just a piece of Python.
つまり､ これはPythonの一部なんだ｡
It's just some, some Python code.
ただのPythonのコードだよ｡
And I'm going to tell you what it does.
そして､ それが何をするものなのかを教えよう｡
So we import modal.
そこで､ モーダルをインポートする｡
And from modal we import a few things.
そして､ モーダルからいくつかのものをインポートする｡
App for applications volume and image.
アプリケーションのボリュームとイメージのためのアプリ｡
Um and actually now that I look at it I see that I don't actually end up using volume.
それに､ 今見てみると､ 結局ボリュームは使っていないんだ｡
So I don't think that is needed.
だから､ その必要はないと思う｡
Keep this simple is better.
シンプルな方がいい｡
Um, and so this is what you do.
それで､ こうするんだ｡
You begin with some setup.
まずはセットアップから始める｡
You tell modal what kind of infrastructure you need.
どのようなインフラが必要かをモーダルに伝える｡
And this is an example of modal talks about this a bit on the in their docs.
これはモーダルの例で､ ドキュメントで少し触れています｡
But this is this is a type of infrastructure as code.
しかし､ これはコードとしてのインフラの一種である｡
You can use code to describe what kind of box you want.
どのような箱が欲しいかをコードで記述することができる｡
So if you're thinking when we're in Google Colab, we had to pick various drop downs and choose what
Google Colabでは､ いろいろなドロップダウンを選んで､
kind of, um, VM, what runtime we wanted from Google Colab, well, here you just get to choose what
どんなVMが欲しいか､ どんなランタイムが欲しいかを選ぶ必要があった｡
So we, we say that we want an image which we want it to be the Debian operating system.
つまり､ Debianオペレーティング・システムのイメージが欲しいということだ｡
We want to pip install the requests package that very, very common standard package for, for uh,
pipでrequestsパッケージをインストールしたい｡ このパッケージは､ URLウェブ作業を行うための､
doing URL web work.
とても一般的な標準パッケージだ｡
Um, and we specify a GPU, uh, actually, which again is also not used in this example.
そして､ GPUを指定するのだが､ これもこの例では使わない｡
Sorry.
申し訳ない｡
That makes it a bit simpler.
これで少しシンプルになった｡
We're not going to use a GPU for this example because we're keeping it very simple indeed.
この例ではGPUを使うつもりはない｡ 非常にシンプルにしているからだ｡
Uh, so uh, the I have got a method called hello.
helloというメソッドがある｡
It's a very simple.
とてもシンプルだ｡
It's a function.
それは機能だ｡
Hello.
こんにちは｡
That returns a string.
これは文字列を返す｡
Uh, and what it does is it imports requests, uh, it gets it goes to a website called IP info.io,
それで何をするかというと､ リクエストをインポートして､ IP情報というウェブサイトにアクセスするんだ｡  これは知っておくと便利だ｡
It's just one of these utilities that will return a JSON object which describes where you are the IP
JSONオブジェクトを返すユーティリティのひとつで､ IPアドレスの場所を記述している｡
Um, and so then I take that JSON, I pull out the city, the region and the country, and I say hello
そのJSONから都市､ 地域､ 国を抜き出し､ 都市､ 地域､ 国からこんにちはと言う｡
Um, and it's just based on your IP address.
ええと､ IPアドレスに基づいているだけです｡
So it's just going to say hello from wherever you are, or at least wherever your ISP is serving you
だから､ あなたがどこにいようと､ 少なくともISPがどこからあなたにサービスを提供していようと､ こんにちはと言うだけだ｡
from.
だから僕にとっては､ ニューヨークにかなり近い場所になるだろうけど､ ニューヨークではないかもしれない｡
Um, so that's a pretty simple function.
それはとてもシンプルな機能だ｡
The only potential interesting thing about it is this decorator at the top here, which is a gradient
このデコレーターはグラデーション・デコレーターで､
decorator where we've decorated it with app, which is this thing here, this modal app.
アプリでデコレートされています｡
Hello dot function.
ハロー・ドット・ファンクション
And then we're passing in this image.
そして､ この画像の中を通過する｡
And that image refers to a Debian image uh which has requests installed.
そして､ そのイメージはDebianのイメージを指しており､ そのイメージにはリクエストがインストールされている｡
And just by decorating it with that, we're saying that's the kind of box that we want to be to be able
このような装飾を施すことで､ 我々が望めばこのような箱でこれを走らせることができると言っているのだ｡
That's all there is to it.
それだけだ｡
So you you could put that to one side.
だから､ そのことは横に置いておいてほしい｡
You could imagine that this was just part of an existing piece of code.
これは既存のコードの一部だと想像できるだろう｡
You had to do something, and now you've just decorated it with something to say that you want to be
あなたは何かをしなければならなかった｡ そして今､ あなたはそれを､ Debianオペレーティングシステムを使い､
able to run it should you wish to, using a Debian operating system with requests installed.
リクエストをインストールした上で､ それを実行できるようにしたいという言葉で飾った｡
So that is all that's in this hello.py.
このハローワークにあるのは以上だ｡  パイ｡
Super simple.
超シンプルだ｡
We go back to day one dot, the Jupyter notebook.
初日のドット､ ジュピター・ノートブックに戻ろう｡
So I'm now going to import that.
だから､ これからそれをインポートする｡
And so now what I can do is I can call my hello I can I can take my hello function that I've, that
そして今できることは､ ここでインポートしたhello関数を呼び出すことだ｡
And I can call it by saying hello dot local.
そして､ ハロー・ドット・ローカルと言って呼ぶことができる｡
And what that means is I want to run that function that I've just defined, that we just looked at this
つまり､ 先ほど定義した関数を､ ローカル・ボックス上で実行したいのだ｡
I want to run it in this Jupyter notebook.
このJupyterノートブックで実行したい｡
Let's see what we get.
何が出てくるか見てみよう｡
So it's running right now.
だから､ 今走っている｡
And it says hello from seaport, New York, US.
アメリカ､ ニューヨークのシーポートからこんにちは｡
That is where my ISP is, I guess.
そこが私のISPなんだと思う｡
Let's try that again.
もう一度やってみよう｡
Yeah, that seems pretty consistent.
ああ､ それはかなり一貫しているようだ｡
So that's running locally.
これがローカルで動いているわけだ｡
Uh, and, uh, now look at this one here.
それと､ これを見てくれ｡
It's exactly the same thing.
まったく同じことだ｡
I've just changed local to remote.
ローカルをリモートに変更したところだ｡
That's the only.
それだけだ｡
The only thing I've changed.
唯一､ 変えたことがある｡
Let's see what happens.
どうなるか見てみよう｡
Let's take a little bit longer and then.
もう少し時間をかけてからにしよう｡
Hello from Ashburn, Virginia, us.
バージニア州アッシュバーンからこんにちは｡
It's running in a completely different state, so I'm sure you you're expecting that.
まったく違う状態で走っているから､ それを期待しているんだろうね｡
You get the idea.
おわかりだろう｡
Uh, and sometimes it's different.
あー､ 時には違うこともある｡
By the way, I've seen it pop up all over the place.
ちなみに､ あちこちで見かけるようになった｡
So simply by calling remote instead of local, you can call this function the same piece of code, the
つまり､ ローカルではなくリモートを呼び出すだけで､ 同じコード､ 同じPythonコードを呼び出すことができる｡
And it's been deployed to a server and it's running on that server instead.
そしてそれはサーバーにデプロイされ､ 代わりにそのサーバーで動いている｡
So I think that's pretty magical.
それはとても不思議なことだと思う｡
It's magical because it's so simple and it's just allowed us to deploy some code.
とてもシンプルで､ いくつかのコードをデプロイするだけでいいのだから､ 魔法のようだ｡
And now we've got a slightly more involved package called llama.
そして今､ 私たちはllamaという少し複雑なパッケージを手に入れた｡
And this is where things like GPUs start to appear.
そしてここからGPUのようなものが登場する｡
You can see I paired this back to the hello example, which is why there was some some traces of what
ハローの例と対になっているのがわかるだろう｡
Um, so I start by, um, uh, calling my app llama.
まず､ 自分のアプリのラマに電話するんだ｡
Um, now I'm going to again have a Debian image, but this time I'm going to install torch transformers,
ええと､ もう一度Debianのイメージを作りますが､ 今回はtorch transformers､ bits and bytesをインストールして､
bits and bytes and accelerate all packages that you know.
皆さんが知っているすべてのパッケージを加速させます｡
Well, at this point, um, I am also getting my hugging face token from my modal secrets, and that
まあ､ この時点で､ うーん､ 僕はモード・シークレットからハグする顔のトークンも手に入れている｡
I will show you in a second how you set that up in modal, how you get to secrets, and you can set
モーダルでどのように設定するか､ どのようにシークレットにアクセスするか､ どのようにハグする顔のトークンを設定するか､
your hugging face token in there.
すぐにお見せしましょう｡
And once you've done that, you can read it like this.
そうしたら､ こう読むことができる｡
And I'm specifying that I want a T4 GPU, which of course is the very cheap basic one.
そして､ 私はT4 GPUが欲しいと指定しているのですが､ それはもちろんとても安いベーシックなものです｡
And I've got a constant here.
そして､ ここには不変のものがある｡
And now I have uh, this, this generate, uh, function.
そして今､ 私はこの､ この､ 生成機能を手に入れた｡
And it takes a prompt which is a string, and it returns a string.
そして､ 文字列であるプロンプトを受け取り､ 文字列を返す｡
This is an example of the type hints.
これはタイプのヒントの例である｡
If you're not familiar with them.
ご存じない方も多いだろう｡
It's something that I'll be doing this time around in various places.
今回もいろいろなところでやることになるだろう｡
And it will, uh, I think, become clear after a bit.
そして､ それは......少し経てば明らかになると思う｡
So, uh, again, I decorate this function with I pass in the image, I tell it my secrets, and I say
この関数を装飾して､ 画像を渡し､ 秘密を伝え､ T4 GPUが欲しいと言うと､
I want a T4 GPU, all configuring my server using code.
コードを使ってサーバーを設定する｡
And now this is just a function as if I were writing something to run locally.
そして今､ これはローカルで実行する何かを書いているかのような単なる関数である｡
Now, I couldn't possibly run this locally because my box has nothing like the horsepower to be able
というのも､ 私のマシンには､ このようなラマ・モデルをローカルで動かせるほどの馬力はないからだ｡
There are ways you can do it with things like llama CP if you're familiar with that, but I wouldn't
リャマCPのようなものに詳しい人ならできる方法もあるだろうけど､ ここに書いてあるようなことは僕にはできないし､
be able to do it like it's written here, and if I did, it would be very, very slow.
やったとしてもとてもとても時間がかかる｡
Um, and so I want to do it on a box which has a T4 GPU and this is how I'll be able to do it.
それで､ T4 GPUを搭載したボックスでそれをやりたいんだ｡
Um, and so this, this code should all look very familiar to you.
ええと､ それで､ このコードはすべて､ あなたにとって非常に見慣れたものに見えるはずです｡
This is the config that you know.
これがあなたが知っているコンフィグだ｡
Well that puts specifies the, the four bit quantization that will have for Lama.
つまり､ 4ビットの量子化をラマに指定することになる｡
Um, we are going to load the tokenizer, this boilerplate stuff, you know.
ええと､ トークナイザーをロードします｡
Well we are going to load our model.
さて､ モデルをロードしよう｡
And then this, you should also recognize we encode the the prompt into tokens as our input.
そして､ 入力としてプロンプトをトークンにエンコードする｡
We set this attention mask to avoid getting that warning.
その警告を受けないように､ このアテンションマスクを設定した｡
And then we do model dot generate.
そして､ モデル・ドット・ジェネレーションを行う｡
We pass in our inputs.
インプットを渡す｡
We say we only need five new tokens and we want to just one response.
新しいトークンは5つだけで､ 返事は1つでいいとする｡
We will take that one response, we will decode it and we will return it.
私たちはその1つのレスポンスを受け取り､ それを解読して返す｡
It's as simple as that.
簡単なことだ｡
Now with that, let's start that and let's run it.
では､ それを実行してみよう｡
So stuff is happening.
だから､ いろいろなことが起きている｡
So, um, first of all, what what have I actually run?
それで､ まず最初に､ 僕は実際に何を走ったんだ？
So I've called the remote function and what I passed in the prompt that I passed in to a llama model
リモート関数を呼び出したわけだが､ ラマモデルに渡したプロンプトの内容は謎だ｡
Everyone must stand alone.
誰もが独り立ちしなければならない｡
I hear now, uh, I, uh, hopefully most people know what comes next from that.
今聞いたところでは､ ええと､ ええと､ 願わくば､ ほとんどの人がそこから次に何が起こるかを知っていてほしい｡
Otherwise I'm going to feel very old.
そうでなければ､ 私はとても年を取ったように感じるだろう｡
Uh, but, uh uh, this, of course, would be straight from the opening to Like a Prayer by Madonna.
ええと､ でも､ ええと､ これはもちろん､ マドンナの『Like a Prayer』のオープニングからそのままなんだけど｡
And I hear you Call my name would be what comes next.
そして､ 次は私の名前を呼ぶと聞いている｡
And it's almost unbearable not to say that.
それを言わないのは､ ほとんど耐え難いことだ｡
Uh, and now I'm going to hear that song in my head for for the rest of the day.
あー､ 今日一日､ 頭の中でこの歌が鳴りっぱなしだ｡
Uh, but, um.
あ､ でも､ あの｡
Yeah.
そうだね｡
And sorry if I've put that now in your in your mind forever too, but, uh, such a catchy song.
そして､ もし僕がそれをいつまでも君の頭の中に置いていたら申し訳ないんだけど､ でも､ とてもキャッチーな曲なんだ｡
Anyway, it's what we're seeing now is what's going on on that box.
とにかく､ 今我々が見ているのは､ あの箱の上で何が起こっているかということだ｡
Um, and we can also flip over to, to modal itself.
そして､ モーダルそのものに切り替えることもできる｡
Um, and uh, let's see, go to the let me refresh this screen.
ええと､ ええと､ この画面をリフレッシュさせてください｡
Uh, so it's not a deployed app.
つまり､ デプロイされたアプリではないんだ｡
Ephemeral apps.
儚いアプリ｡
That's what it is.
そういうことだ｡
Uh, give me a second to find that.
ちょっと待ってください｡
So this is it.
それでこれだ｡
Running right now.
今走っている｡
Running as an ephemeral app, uh, generates, um, started two minutes ago.
エフェメラルなアプリとして動いている｡
And we can click into it and we can see that its status is running.
クリックすると､ ステータスが実行中であることがわかる｡
Uh, and, uh, let's see what else we can get.
それと､ 他に何が手に入るかな？
So the containers, it's live.
だから､ コンテナはライブなんだ｡
We can look at the memory, the CPU cores.
メモリやCPUコアを見ることができる｡
And we can see it's a T4 GPU, just as we specified.
そして､ 我々が指定した通り､ T4 GPUであることがわかる｡
Um, and we can also look at the we can see that Hello.py is also on this box we just ran.
そして､ "ハロー "を見ることもできる｡  PYは今走ったこのボックスにもある｡
And llama.py uh, is sitting there, the, the Python script that we just wrote.
そしてラマ｡  さっき書いたPythonスクリプトが置いてある｡
Uh, so here we go.
ええと､ それではどうぞ｡
While we're here, I'm just going to point out that right at the top here is secrets.
ここにいる間に指摘しておきたいのは､ ここの一番上にあるのは秘密だということだ｡
And secrets is, of course, where you go to set the secrets, the hugging face token.
そしてシークレットはもちろん､ シークレットをセットする場所である｡
So you will need to do that.
だから､ そうする必要がある｡
I'm not going to click on that now to avoid revealing my hugging face token secret.
ハグしている顔の形見の秘密がバレないように､ 今はそれをクリックするつもりはない｡
Um, but that's that's where you would go so that you can then use your hugging face token in the code
でもそこで､ このエフェメラル・サービスにデプロイされたコードで､
that's deployed in your ephemeral, uh, service here.
ハグする顔のトークンを使えるようにするんだ｡
So it's still running.
だからまだ動いている｡
And I think at this point I will hold to this video.
この時点で､ 私はこのビデオに固執すると思う｡
And when I come back, uh oh, it's already just said it's succeeded.
で､ 戻ってきたら､ ああ､ もう成功したって書いてある｡
Uh, and I did just get a message saying that it had finished as well.
ええと､ ちょうど終了したというメッセージも受け取ったところだ｡
Uh, and, uh.
ええと､ それで...｡
Let's see.
見てみよう｡
Yes.
そうだ｡
Back here.
ここに戻る｡
Let's see what we get.
何が出てくるか見てみよう｡
I hear you call my name.
私の名前を呼ぶ声が聞こえる｡
Uh, so, lama, even the four bit quantized version of Lama also couldn't resist completing the Madonna
ええと､ だから､ ラマ､ 4ビット量子化バージョンのラマも､ マドンナの曲を完成させないわけにはいかなかったんだ｡
Uh, and so we have just successfully run this piece of code.
ええと､ それで､ このコードを実行することに成功しました｡
Um, using this ephemeral, uh, service on modal, uh, to run a quantized lama, um, uh, model,
このエフェメラルな､ あー､ モーダルなサービスを使って､ あー､ 量子化されたラマ､ あー､ モデル､ あー､ ラマ3を走らせる｡
All right.
プロンプトを完成させるモデル1名｡
When we come back, we are going to go through and it's going to be time for us to deploy our model
また戻ってきたら､ モデルをデプロイして､ 前回構築した独自モデルの周りにAPIをどのように配置するか､
and actually see how we do that and how we put an API around the proprietary model that we built last
実際にやって見よう｡
I will see you in a minute.
すぐに会おう｡